So today we'll not talk about CQL we'll
talk about uh reasoning um and uh sort
of particularly LL reinforcement
learning for LLM reasoning. So at a high
level reasoning could mean many many
things for and it it clearly even today
means different things for different
people. Uh but what I'm going to do uh
today in this lecture um uh and also I
should mention that like it's very hard
to kind of do justice to reasoning
topics in sort of one lecture. Uh this
was also a trouble that I had for my own
class this semester where I was kind of
covering similar content like two weeks
ago. Uh and I couldn't go over
everything. But what I'm going to do
today is to sort of give you at least
one perspective on some of the trends in
the field of reasoning. And for doing
that what we'll do is we'll restrict
ourselves to sort of solving math
problems. So uh you know if you're
following all the news in in in language
models these days uh sort of people have
been really excited about solving uh
sort of technical questions like math
and coding and scientific questions with
these models. And one of sort of the the
benchmarks people look at for example is
this a IME exam American invitational
mathematical examination. uh this is
sort of an example question okay uh from
from uh from that particular exam where
uh you kind of have to solve u a certain
sort of number theory question for
instance and uh and and to solve this uh
sort of these are some ground solutions
for it you'll have to solve this in
natural language where you kind of want
your language model for instance to you
know see after seeing this question
produce a solution that looks like one
of those solutions that you see up on
the slide uh so I took these solutions
from sort of the the ground truth sort
of the reference solutions that exist
for this exam but you would want want
your LLM to sort of be capable enough to
one, you know, write a solution like
this and two, come up with the right
answer finally. So that's sort of sort
of the goal for today. So uh what I'll
do today is I'll give you sort of my
perspective on or or sort of I'll
organize the material in reasoning and
especially RL for reasoning in sort of a
particular way that I particularly like
and to do that we'll start off from um
sort of the conventional way or looking
back at the conventional way of training
language models. So typically when we
train language models or or just
generally foundation models overall the
the conventional paradigm has to do has
been to do next token prediction meaning
you take your data you tokenize that
into a string of uh sort of uh tokens uh
token inputs and you train the model
with sort of a negative log likelihood
loss to predict the next token that
appears in the sequence. So in the
context of reasoning this would mean you
would take uh the question you would
tokenize it into a string of tokens.
You'll take the answer which is from one
of these reference solutions, tokenize
that into a string of tokens and then
train the model to predict this answer
string conditioned on the input question
string.
Now to start to look at or start to
understand why RL matters here, uh we'll
start by asking this question of why
does next token prediction of this form
actually work. And um you know again
this answering this question will take
uh sort of more than it's an open
research question to be honest. But one
perspective of looking at this that I
particularly like is to sort of look at
this particular equation which tells you
how well next token prediction works in
general. So what is this equation
telling me? It's telling me that if I
train a model, if I train a particular
model P theta which is mapping some
inputs X like the question to some
output Y like the answer this learned
model is only going to approximate sort
of the ground trth underlying model or
the ground truth solution uh with a with
an error meaning with an error that is
shown on the slide which is P theta
minus P star depending on the size of
the data that you used for training. So
if you have a lot of data which shows
you uh many many questions and many many
answers then ideally this error would be
low and you would kind of approximate
sort of a very high cap highly capable
expert at solving these questions. But
in reality uh it so happens that the
amount of data that you have for a lot
of these reasoning problems or and and
many other domains as well you you you
really don't have enough data to make
this bound small enough. So you kind of
end up learning models that are not
approximating human level capabilities
if you just do next open prediction. So
there's actually sort of a lot of work
that exists out there which studies the
amount of data and one of the
interesting things that they tell you is
uh if you simply keep doing um you if
you simply keep taking highquality
solutions of of of hard questions from
the internet and you train your model
with uh some sort of supervised training
some sort of next token prediction you
will kind of not do really well because
it's estimated that you're going to run
out of high quality data of this sort by
2028. And clearly you have not gotten to
a level where you can do great research
with or these models can just replace
human uh researchers for instance. This
also happens in other domains uh like
for instance in in robotics and embodied
AI where again data is very limited
which means that if if you just simply
rely on next token prediction alone
you'll not be able to get the ground
truth sort of expert level capability in
your model of sorts.
Um so just to kind of give you a a
concrete example uh you know if you just
train models on current data and you ask
them to solve this very interesting
question from IMO 2021 uh presumably
this question exists in the training
sets of one of these models but if you
ask sort of GPD or open AI family of
models to solve this they're going to
give you a solution that kind of looks
very sensible uh in the in these
settings. So you know they're going to
produce solutions that look quite quite
like a solution that a human expert
would have written except that they end
up missing the logic behind the the
answer. So in this particular question
if you need to prove that inequality
that you see up on the slide you cannot
really go out there and and start to
look at individual terms of that
expression. You have to kind of think
about the whole summation as a whole.
And you know these models this is I
think from uh from an O series model I
think 01
that that I kind of got the solution. Uh
it starts to look at sort of individual
terms. for instance uh and ends up kind
of asserting uh its solution at the end
but really kind of does not realize that
it's actually making a mistake and does
not correct it. So really what ends up
happening with these current sort of
supervised training paradigms when you
think about reasoning is that they're
going to produce a solution that looks
very much like a legitimate solution
that you could have written on an exam
is just that that solution ends up being
wrong and the logical content of that
solution is not quite correct.
And that's precisely something that RL
tries to fix. And I'll you know
hopefully try to show you some some
examples today of what what kind of RL
techniques come to rescue in that
setting.
So uh in today's lecture uh I guess
we'll talk about RL for reasoning. Um I
roughly uh sort of characterized this in
in in in sort of two parts or I broke
this into two parts and these two parts
are based on sort of timeline. So it's
based on like stuff that came before
sort of the DeepS R1 family of models
came out. How many of you know what the
Deepseek R1 model is? Actually I'm just
curious or have have seen it have played
around with it. It's a it's a model that
was released which is from a company in
China named Deepseek which is really
really good at solving a lot of these
sort of competition math problems or
competition coding problems. Um it's
sort of in a similar vein similar style
of model as the openio series of models
or some of these thinking models that
exist out there like the Gemini thinking
model or sort of claude sonnet thinking
version etc. So these are sort of models
of the same family and what we're going
to do is we're going to talk about
techniques that came before these models
came out which is early 2025 so January
2025 and some techniques that that kind
of have become much more prominent in
the community after these models came
out. So uh the first part of my lecture
will be based on these classical
techniques that I'm going to talk about
and I'll talk about techniques that uh
rely on some form of imitation learning
which I'm guessing has been covered in
the class. We'll talk about some
techniques that look like offline
reinforcement learning. Um, and I'll
talk about some techniques that look
like online reinforcement learning. Um,
this is sort of my characterization of
this whole space. Um, in general,
there's a lot of literature that has
been coming out. So, I'll probably miss
out on some of them, but this is roughly
a characterization that I think makes
sense to to think about. And after that
I'm going to talk about some modern
extensions of these techniques into sort
of this uh you know into this thinking
model uh kind of territory where we'll
talk about how can you take some of
these techniques that people have built
uh you know before uh early 2025 and
think about using them to train thinking
models that that have been doing really
amazing right now. And there's some very
um sort of interesting things that need
to change when you go from the first the
left hand side to the right hand side in
this particular uh setting.
Okay. So, uh I guess I already talked
about the the the problem setup, but uh
let me kind of just quickly go into a
little bit of a detail uh and and
connect back to RL terminology. So, uh
we going to consider reasoning and uh
you know in this particular setting as I
described earlier you'll be given a
problem in natural language and you have
to write a solution in natural language.
So, what we can do when you think about
this in the context of RL from an RL
person's lens is you can think of this
whole uh problem solving as an MDP as a
markoff decision process. And to do
that, what you can do is you can think
of the string of tokens that exist in
the or string of words that exist in the
in the question as sort of an initial
state of your MDP. Um, so it's sort of
the initial state that your agent or
your policy is going to start from uh
when it starts to sort of act in the
world. You can think of uh sort of this
solution that the model produces u you
know as being broken down into a
sequence of steps uh and these steps
could correspond to actions for example.
So you can think of it as you know
there's a model which uh which takes as
input this initial state which is the
problem. It one by one takes in a bunch
of actions which are these steps and at
the ends up with a particular answer. So
in this particular setting that answer
is represented in this sort of uh you
know in this box that you see up there
um and the answer is eight. And what
you're going to do is you're going to
reward the model with a sparse reward of
plus one if this answer ends up being
correct.
uh and a reward of zero if this answer
does not end up being correct. So the
real mark of decision process here is
sort of state going to a sequence of
actions and going to sort of a you know
a termination bit where the model
produces an answer and you get a reward
at the end of it when if the if the if
the particular answer is correct or not.
So in RL terminology this is a lot like
a sparse reward MDP with a deterministic
dynamics. What do I mean by this?
Basically uh there's no external
environment in this whole process of
producing these steps. There's no
external environment that gives you a
next state. All you are seeing is the
initial state and these actions one by
one which tell you the the next state of
the problem. So I'll just draw on the
board because uh I I think you know so
this is your initial state your model
takes as action you know the particular
step the first step of the problem it
gets to state s1 which is nothing but
the string of tokens in s0 and a z
concatenated with each other so that's
all s1 is it it produces the next state
a1 next it takes the next step a1 or
next action a1 goes to s2 and your next
state s2 is just s0 a 0 a1 on
concatenate with each other until you
hit the final answer. So you know you do
this multiple times you hit the final
answer your model produces some answer
let's say eight uh you get a reward
which is based on you know whether 8 is
equal to the ground truth uh answer or
not. So you get a reward of arg of 8
comma ground truth. This is either plus
one or zero. That's your mdp that you're
operating at. So that's a very good
question. So the actions here could be
infinity. Uh there are infinitely many
actions. But unlike sort of having
unless continuous control where you kind
of have you know a fixed dimension
vector of many of continuous values
which are also infinite you have a
variable length string of tokens which
are which are all discrete but then
there could be many of them. So the
question is uh what about questions
where the answer is a answer is a proof
or not a not a final numerical value. Uh
that's a very good question. Uh I think
we uh as a community haven't figured out
the right set of techniques for such
problems. So that's why we started off
with sort of competition problems where
there is a sort of a deterministic final
answer uh in some way. So we'll assume
for now that we have a deterministic
final answer we end with. Yeah. So the
question is is there a risk that we get
to the right answer but we take
suboptimal steps. Uh there is and I'm
going to be talking about that uh in
this lecture actually. Yeah. So that's
sort of a a basic sort of you know
reasoning MDP or a language MDP you can
pose for for studying reasoning problems
in this particular setting and at least
something that I'm going to be sticking
to uh in this particular lecture.
Okay. So, we'll start with studying some
classical RL methods for reasoning. Uh,
and what I'm going to do here is I'm
going to cover one of my papers uh from
Europe4 that you see on the slide. This
is the the first bullet point. Uh, and
why am I covering that paper? It's not
because this paper invented a lot of the
techniques, but because this paper
actually did a lot of sort of lot of
interesting empirical analysis of a lot
of the methods that exist out there to
kind of understand why something works
and why something fails. uh so it's just
sort of a nice way to kind of get a
conceptual model at least in my opinion
about all the sort of techniques in the
classical uh reasoning space with RL
okay so what we're going to do is we're
going to uh sort of try to understand
how different methods or how you know RL
methods for training for reasoning
behave when we scale when we train them
on different amounts of data so we're
going to do what we call a data scaling
analysis in this particular segment of
the talk so the basic setup here would
be I'm going
build algorithms that can uh that can be
used to train uh reasoning models uh on
a data set right this data set will
consist of some problems or these
initial states that I described to you
earlier um and we'll assume access to
some oracle solutions because we need a
way to like check the ground truth
answer because that defines the reward
function so we have a data set of
problems and and solutions that we're
going to be training with and what we're
going to do is we're going to try to
understand different classes of methods
by evaluating how well they do when we
train them on different amounts problems
and solution pairs that uh that this
data set gives us.
So there's three axis we're going to
look at when we think about uh you know
training these methods on on on this
data. We can train them with potentially
uh you know ground truth answers on
multiple questions. So we can take uh
this data set of problems and solutions
and train the model to produce the
solution given the question like what
supervised fine-tuning or uh you know
imitation learning does. So we can just
do imitation learning on top of this
data. We'll introduce a new method that
we call uh sort of uh you know rejection
fine-tuning which trains on many correct
solutions for a given answer. So I'm
going to write this uh method out here u
and uh oops and that'll be clear for
you. So what you're going to do is
you're going to take a model pi of y
given x. We'll take a a question x from
my data set. So this is my question
or problem. So this is my initial state.
This is my solution which consists of a
sequence of actions. What I'm going to
do now is I'm going to take uh these
questions and sample multiple solutions
from my particular model my from my
current model that I want to train in
this particular setting. So I have a
model pi theta. I'm going to sample
multiple solutions conditioned on the
question given
this particular uh uh model. So this is
my model. I'm training the initial
model.
This is the data set. I'm going to
sample multiple solution traces. What
I'm going to do now is I'm going to take
these traces,
evaluate the rewards on each of them. So
I'm going to evaluate R of R of Y1
uh R of Y2
R of YN. Why can I do this? because I
have this question in my data set which
means I have a ground trth answer Ystar
for this question in my data set as
well. Ground truth answer for X
question.
And what I can do is I can simply match
whether multiple traces or multiple
trajectories sampled from my policy pi
theta end up in the right answer or not
by checking the you know checking
whether the final number was correct or
not. So what I'm doing here is I'm
taking my initial model sampling a bunch
of traces or you know rolling it out in
my environment which is simply producing
solutions from this model for each
question and evaluating the rewards
against the ground truth answer. Now
what I do is I take this particular uh
set of y1 to yns I produced and I retain
only those ones which ended up in a
right answer. So I take the set S of Y1
to YN
and I filter it to get some filtered set
let's call it S till day which consists
of Y's
so Y J such that the reward is one
meaning these uh solutions ended up at
the right answer. Does this procedure
make sense to people? Okay. And what I'm
going to do now is, you know, now I have
a bunch of traces or a bunch of
trajectories that ended up at the right
answer, which means they're successful.
So what I can do is I can simply try to
train my model pi theta to imitate these
trajectories. So I can train pi theta to
imitate s uh sild. So I'm just going to
write it down here again. Uh so my
algorithm looks like this for iteration
one to you know some t that I can choose
however I want sample. So step one is
sample
y1's to n uh y1 to n from pi theta of
dot given x question.
Uh the second step is filter
uh and and generate S till day which
consists of correct
Y1 uh correct Y's only
and the third step is uh do imitation or
do BC or SFT depending upon whatever
terminology you like you can call that
on S t. So you're training the model now
pi theta to produce only the y's that
were correct. So that's sort of this
this particular approach.
Okay. So this approach is what is called
uh rejection fine-tuning or rft. And
that's why you see on the on the on the
on the horizontal axis up there where
what you're doing now is you're going to
produce many solutions and try to filter
for correct correct ones and train on
them. Again
what happens now is you're rejecting the
ones that were wrong. Hence the word
rejection and fine-tuning just stands
for fine-tuning. So RF or rejection
finetuning. The nice property about this
approach is it's not actually asking you
for Oracle solutions that a human wrote.
All it asks for is solutions that uh
that you your model can produce which
ended up being correct. So these are on
policy rollouts that are sampled from
your policy and you're simply filtering
for correctness which you can because
you know what the reward function looks
like.
And the third axis here is actually
full-blown reinforcement learning where
you know in RL when we train on data we
don't really need the data to be high
quality or high rewarding. You know
you've talked about offline RL that's on
your homework. You can learn from
suboptimal data data that does not
succeed. And so you can kind of also
think about you know the third access in
all of these methods as methods which
train on incorrect solutions or learn
from traces or rollouts that did not
succeed that attained a reward of zero.
So I'm just going to call them R. So
there are these three different axis
along which you can sort of you know
train methods. You can scale your data.
You can scale your your model uh model
bandwidth number of questions and
solutions SFT number of questions and
correct solutions by filtering or
rejection which is called rejection
finetuning or RF and just training on
any kind of data which is reinforcement
learning. So what I'm going to do in
this lecture is we'll talk about how
these different methods actually behave
in practice and that'll give us a sense
of like what to use in what case. So the
question is are we forcing the model to
come up with overly verbose answers. Uh
so here we are not really uh so the
answer the short answer is no because
here we are not really encouraging
verbosity at all. All we're doing is
we're simply sampling multiple traces
from a model and training the model to
find answers find uh to to train the
model to sort of uh you know closely
mimic traces which ended up being uh
successful in some way. So if the traces
that end up being successful are those
that actually need more space to be
verbose, then it's going to incentivize
you to be verbose. But if the questions
that end up succeeding are not those or
the traces that end up succeeding are
not the ones that end up needing to be
verbose, then it's going to not
incentivize it. So imagine that let's
say the question is 2 plus 2 is equal to
question mark. Maybe one of the traces
gets you an answer of four. And you know
there are some traces which are going to
do this do which are going to count 2
plus two in 10 different ways but most
of the traces write down four right
away. Then what you're going to do in
this process is you're going to find
traces which end up with a four right
away and you're going to train them all
to produce four right away uh as the
next token. So it's not necessarily
going to happen that way. Okay. So the
question is if I if the method got the
correct answer with the wrong sort of
approach then you're incentivizing the
model to learn that. Uh and the answer
is yes and that's why we'll see how
these things behave in empirical
results. That's kind of the next part of
the talk. Yes.
>> Yeah. So the question is would the data
set be biased towards easy problems? Uh
the the short answer is uh it does yes
uh in some way. Uh but the the the the
practical answer for this question is
well in in these cases what you're going
to do is you're going to potentially
start with training the model uh on top
of Oracle data or Oracle question answer
pairs uh first with SFT the the first
access that goes up and then do
rejection fine tuning on top of it. So
the model has some capability now to
produce some answers for those questions
and then you start doing it. Great. So
this was actually one of the slides
which takes the which took me a long
time even in my lecture uh back then but
uh a lot of the slides from here on are
actually talking about properties of
these methods actually. So the first
thing we're going to look at is how does
SFT behave so training your model with
like imitation learning on correct
answers given questions that some human
wrote. So when we're doing this work we
uh looked at two benchmarks um uh named
GSM 8K and and math. these benchmarks
now are fully solved. So you know it
doesn't doesn't make sense to sort of
going forward benchmark methods on these
benchmarks. But uh back then in 2024
this was like a year ago exactly uh
these benchmarks are very uh sort of
representative of like useful methods.
So what we try to do in this uh
particular u uh slide is we trying to
see how well SFT behaves comp and
comparing it to and we're trying to
compare it to RFT or rejection fining
that I described to you. We do that on
top of multiple models. And here I'm
showing you one result on top of the
DeepSeek V2 model that uh that was one
of the best math models back at the
time. And what I'm plotting here is I'm
plotting the average test error of these
model after fine-tuning with these SFT
and RF methods as a function of how much
data we run fine-tuning on. So the more
the data, the ideal picture is you will
get lower error and you should be able
to actually get better accuracy, right?
Because you have more data, more
coverage of questions like that. So that
indeed does happen. So you do find that
you know error goes down as you scale up
the amount of questions in both of these
settings. Uh but clearly uh sort of the
error does not go down at a very fast
rate. Meaning uh it so turns out that
you know the test error if you try to
like approximate the closest sort of uh
function to this particular curve it'll
be it'll be the function that looks like
d to the minus.15 or d to the minus.05.
So this particular curve that you're
seeing these are empirical measurements.
But if I try to fit a smooth curve to it
as a function of the data set size that
the exponent is going to be a very small
number. Ideally you would want this
exponent to be really large like you
know d to the minus half for instance
because this curve will go down very
quickly and with a reasonable amount of
data you're going to be succeeding at
the particular problem at this
particular data set but that doesn't
happen in this case. So one of the goals
that we then then could have for a lot
of these reasoning methods and and RL
methods uh for reasoning is to sort of
push this curve as much as possible
towards the left and towards uh towards
sort of the x-axis. So so push them down
and towards the left and the first
result we saw to that extent was the
fact that rejection fine tuning or
training on your on your own data on
your own uh correct solutions actually
gets you a much better test error. So
you find that uh sort of you can get the
same test error on both of these
benchmarks uh with RFT as you could do
with 2x the number of questions and 2x
the number of human written solutions
for SFD.
So what this tells you at a high level
is that uh sort of on policy imitation
learning sampling from your policy and
imitating the correct answers can be 2x
more efficient in this particular
setting compared to SFT alone or or off
policy SF or just imitation learning
alone. Okay, great. So, um, so that's
sort of the first result, first takeaway
to have here. But it so turns out that
if you simply keep doing this over and
over, uh, it's not going to give you,
uh, the best possible, uh, policy or the
best possible model. So, if you simply
keep scaling up SFD on on policy data,
what do I mean by scaling it up? I mean
you increase this value of N that you
see up here. So, you just sample tons
and tons of solutions and pick the
correct ones and just start to, you
know, do BC on all of them. Turns out
that that recipe does not actually work.
So what happens is on policy image
learning ends up hurting generalization
if you do too much of it. And to show a
result for it I'm going to show you a
plot here which is showing u sort of the
the the test performance. So the same
plot as but now the x-axis is uh the
number of correct answers you get in
this filtered set that I was describing
to you earlier per question. So you can
scale it up for how muchever you want. S
till day the size of S till day
multiplied by a constant factor is shown
on the X-axis and we are plotting the
performance of the resulting RFD trained
model. The interesting thing to notice
here is that you know initially your
error goes down. So as you do more and
more correct solution traces as you
generate more and more of these correct
solution traces your error goes down as
you see initially but then beyond a
point your error starts to go up uh in
this particular setting. So you find
that like you know beyond the point you
hit diminishing returns and there's no
way you can simply generate more
solutions from your policy mimic them
and get better performance and in fact
the error even goes up on some of these
data sets that you see up here.
>> It's the number of it's you can think of
it as s uh the size of s ta so number of
correct solutions you retain per
question. Uh so the question was the
what is the x axis? The x axis is number
of s.
Uh so the the plot it's basically s till
day time 8k uh in the plot uh because uh
you know that's the number of prompts
that you see up here. But but yeah uh
it's it's just a constant multiplier
which stays same for all the points on
the particular plot. So that's a great
question. So the question is when you
scale S till date which is for RFD do
you do dduplication? Um uh the answer is
yes. Uh and I actually removed that
detail from my slide because I thought
it would be too much details but uh
since you asked it the answer is yes.
You would often when you do this
process, you would often dduplicate as
still days. Uh there's a lot of
mechanisms for it. People can do sort of
uh you know just edit distance based
sort of rejection as well. So keep the
you know sample more than n. So one of
the recipes people do is sample more
than n like 2 n and retain the n of them
which actually seem to be maximally
diverse. That's something people do a
lot of times. So yeah you do that kind
of thing. Great. Okay. So uh what this
tells us at a high level is that fitting
on self-generated data on a limited
number of initial states actually hurts
generalization of the model. So if you
recall the picture that I drew earlier
which I erased where there was an snot
and your model took an A not and got
went to S1. You can think of this as
basically training on a set of snots and
evaluating on a new set on a new test
set pro test problem. And turns out that
if you train too much on a particular
set of snots in this particular way, you
end up hitting the generalization
bottleneck in that setting.
Okay. So why does this happen? And this
is sort of uh the picture I'm going to
talk about uh and I'll connect it to
some of the interesting concepts that we
know in imitation learning right now
which is this picture of spurious steps.
So uh yeah so what we're going to do is
you know we'll move away a little bit
from like examples and look at pictures
and what we'll do is we'll plot these
pictures as I was describing to you
earlier as this little trajectory in an
MDP. So you have prompts as initial
states and you are producing these steps
one by one. they take you to the next
states and then eventually you end up at
the answer. So it so happens that when
you sample a lot from your own model and
train on it on policy like you sample
from your policy and train on it you'll
often find that there are some of these
traces which end up having steps which
are spurious in nature steps which
actually are incorrect but they just
somehow don't affect the model's
generation. So uh I'm going to show you
an example but uh basically these are
steps which would take you to a regime
where you're maybe doing a wrong
calculation uh you know somehow you know
you you get there maybe on this
particular trace when you are sampling
your from your model you end up do
recovering from these traces so you end
up at the correct answer but maybe in
reality uh you know these traces are
actually harmful. So just to give you an
example let's say this is a little
arithmetic problem uh it's from this
GSM8K data set. One interesting example
we found which is the most stark example
of this particular uh issue was uh you
know there's a solution from the model
which does some calculation then it says
that uh you know the total amount of
money needed is like 100 * 2 which is
200 and it reverses its calculation in
the next line. So it you know the the
true calculation is 100 by two but it
ends up saying 200 and then sort of goes
to 100 by two right away. So what ends
up happening is this particular step
that exists in the middle where it's
doing 200 is sort of a spurious step.
It's a step that is not needed. It's a
it's an incorrect step that exists in
the solution. You end up still at the
right answer in this particular rollout,
but this step shouldn't be there uh in
in reality in that particular setting.
So that's a spurious step in in this
particular setting. So the question is
the step is always a sentence for now.
You can imagine it's always a sentence
in this particular setting. There's no
universal universally agreed upon
definition to it. So this is a very sort
of uh I guess in the second part of my
talk, I'm going to show you some
examples where the step is not at all a
sentence. It's a full block of things.
So yeah, that's a great question. So uh
so the question is is there um is this
the main cause of increase in error and
can you not measure it in some way? U so
uh turns out that the answer to both is
yes. It's it's one of the main causes
for increase in error. The can you
measure it in some way at least normal
notions of fitting the data won't tell
you this. That's a great question. So
the question is can we associate the
overfitting problem to this? So you can
actually measure this. In the paper we
did measure this. We measure the amount
of spurious steps that you see and it
grows on over time. Obviously, I cannot
give you a proof that this is the only
cause, right? I I can give you a proof
that this should be a problem. I cannot
give you a proof that this is the only
problem. But this is sort of one of the
one of the big problems that you see. So
the question is how do you find out if
this step in our experiments? We do it
in a particular way and that also
dictates a lot of methodologies that I'm
going to show you in a second. So this
particular method sample uh so the
question is do you sample entire
trajectories? This particular method
samples entire trajectories. uh you can
sample parts of trajectories if you want
it to be but I think it needs some
advanced machinery that I think can be
done based on what I'm going to talk
about in the next slide. That's a great
question. So the question is do you
overfit to a certain class of methods
that got to the right answer in a way
the answer is uh at a high level yes uh
with the caveat that I don't know how to
define what a method means right so you
can call a method that so so just seeing
this example one can say that the the
calculation of 100* 2 is a
methodological phenomena that the model
wants to do to be able to then succeed
uh and then realize that it was wrong.
Uh you can also say that you know really
the method here is nothing but just
doing a bunch of arithmetic. So it
really depends on what you define that
and I I think it's a semantic uh
question at that point but yeah there
are so from a very like sort of symbolic
perspective one can say there are set of
tokens that maybe still lead you to the
right answer on on a training set but
may not actually help you do the right
thing on a test set on a test problem.
So, so this is very similar to the
problem of causal confusion uh in
imitation learning. U actually uh I'm
not sure if causal confusion. Okay.
Okay. Okay. Uh never mind. But basically
there's this problem of like you know if
you if you produce a bunch of um bunch
of u uh stuff uh in your in your policy
that uh you know might be might be bad
like these pious steps you might just
not learn to imitate the expert in the
right way possible. So you know maybe
you you actually like uh end up at the
right answer but you're learning these
incorrect associations. That's basically
the gist of this problem of causal
confusion that people in imitation
learning know a lot about actually.
Okay. So how can we address this and
that's where RL comes in and that's sort
of the third axis of using incorrect
data or incorrect rollouts for learning.
The simple idea is uh you know as many
of you already asked questions about you
know assigning some notion of a credit
to a step. So if I can understand you
know what is the is the utility of every
single step or every single state that
my my policy generates then I can kind
of somehow use that notion to filter off
uh these bad uh kinds of solutions in
some way. Um so that's exactly kind of
what we do or what you know RL for
reasoning tries to do at a high level as
well. So uh identifying these PI steps
and eliminating them in some way. So the
way to do this is uh the following and
you know this ties back to a lot of
concepts of value functions and
advantage functions that many of you are
probably familiar with. Uh so I'm going
to start with an illustration and then
I'll write down the exact math for what
this means. So let's say I gave you a
particular rollout or a particular trace
you know so again starting from a prompt
adding these steps or actions and going
to these uh going to a final answer
which maybe ended up being incorrect. So
it's shown as a red dot. What I can do
now is you know I can try to identify
whether a step is purious or not by
doing uh by taking these particular
prefixes or taking these particular
states that were basically concatenating
all the tokens so far and doing what you
can think of as uh as rollouts in a way.
So I can ask some model to try to
complete the solution given uh a prefix
of a generated solution. So you know for
example in this particular setting that
you see on the slide I have kept the
first three steps the same uh and I'm
asking a separate model or a separate
rollout policy to try to complete the
solution given uh this particular
prefix. I can do this uh you know so so
so if I do this and and let's say the
rollout ends up succeeding so you know
many of these rollouts end up at the
right answer then likely the prefix was
not too bad because clearly for this
particular rollout policy it did not end
up affecting uh any of these uh any any
of its uh you know problem solving
abilities
on the other hand let's say if I ended
up at a at a totally wrong answer
condition on the prefix that you see up
here uh clearly something is not okay
here and clearly there's something wrong
with the with the prefix uh that you're
seeing up here because your rollout
policy could not at all succeed
condition on that prefix you know even
after doing many possible rollouts
and if I ended up succeeding sometimes
and sometimes not maybe there's still
some issue maybe it's not the best thing
you can have but at least uh it's
slightly better than you know always
failing that you see up here for
instance
so this basic principle of doing
rollouts and estimating some notion of
expected success in the future can kind
of tell you something about what is
wrong with the current prefix that you
are that you are particularly operating
at.
This is also very similar to a value
function, right? Because this is
basically computing the expected future
01 reward that my rollout policy that
this orange policy gets when it acts in
this particular MDP.
So uh the question is uh the the
spurious step on the previous slide uh
is that actually uh actually irrelevant
or or or incorrect uh or irrelevant
slash I mean it's incorrect clearly
because or okay the step is not
incorrect in its own own right but it's
it is sort of irrelevant in a way uh
imagine for a second that if you pass to
a language model uh a million irrelevant
tokens and ask it to sort of dig out the
information that actually matters that
that can be a challenging problem on a
test set. So that's why even if a step
is irrelevant uh it can be a problem uh
for the model. Okay. So we did these
rollouts we computed the expected value
of how many times can I succeed and that
resembles something that looks like a
value function of sorts. Uh you know and
why is it a value function? Because uh
if you sort of write this down in a bit
of math uh you know so let's say if I
define the problem or the initial state
as x each of these steps as y1s to yns.
So you know I guess there's a bit of a
notation mismatch here. Y1's to Yns are
independent rollouts. Here the yis I'm
showing are basically each step or each
action that you take. So uh if you write
down if you define a quantity that that
looks like the following uh it's
basically a Q function. So what is this
quantity? It's telling you the Q value
for your particular rollout policy pi
till day. So the policy which is trying
to complete the solution rollout policy
py I'm computing its Q value at a given
state given by the initial state and the
prefix of the solution so far and given
an action which is the current step that
your policy adds. I can define the Q
value here as the expected long-term
reward meaning the expected 01 reward
that I get under my rollout policy if I
start by executing you know a if I start
by getting actions I + 1 to L from this
rollout policy so what's the Q function
a Q function just to recall Q pi I guess
it's subscript pi qi of SA is basically
nothing but um R of essay uh or I guess
depends upon how you write this but it's
basically the expected
discounted reward that you get
uh starting from t equal to 0 to you
know let's say infinity uh in general
conditioned on s0 being s and a 0 being
a this is the definition of a q function
in this particular setting we are
assuming discount factor is one so gamma
is set to exactly
And the reward that you get is only at
termination. So you know there's 0 0 0
until you end up hitting the final
answer. So that's why you see there's
only one expectation up there. And this
expectation is computed under policy pi.
So you compute you roll this policy pi
out u uh from from there on. There's one
minor detail here. You typically have r
of sa plus this thing because you roll
out the policy from the next step and
you sum up the reward at the current
state. In this case it doesn't matter
because r of sa is equal to zero. you
only get a reward at the end. Gamma is
set to one. So essentially the thing
that you see up here is essentially an
expected future reward starting from a
given prefix which is the state at a
given step at a given step which is the
action and the the you know the roll out
is performed under pi till day that you
see up here. Uh okay so the question is
would you use the same policy to roll
out those other trajectories. Um so in
principle this equation that I wrote is
is agnostic of which policy you use to
do the roll out. uh most of so there's
been actually no um so I have a belief
about this answer uh about this
particular uh choice of the policy uh so
in my opinion the the policy that you're
doing rollout switch should be a
different policy compared to the current
one otherwise it can fail in the same
way uh there's some work in literature
which argues that even using the same
policy can actually be good enough um I
think we haven't seen an applesto apples
comparison u given the sort of scale of
experiments which definitively shows one
way or the other Uh I think most of the
evidence that exists right now points
towards the benefits from having a
different policy because that makes
sense also. Uh but I think there's a
part of the community especially sort of
the NLP community which kind of does it
using the same policy and find it finds
it to work reasonably fine.
>> That's a that's a great question. So the
question is uh is this similar to
trajectory stitching and advantage
weights? Uh it so turns out that the
answer is exactly yes. Um it is very
related to that. I don't think I have a
discuss discussion of this stitching
angle in the in my slides because I
think it would have been a bit too
technical but uh yeah if you check the
paper you'll find exactly it talks about
uh sort of stitching in this particular
setting and it's very related concepts
so yeah you can think of it that way
okay great so so this is the definition
of a Q function and and you know once
you've defined this Q function uh you
know it so turns out that you can use
this Q function to now tell you whether
uh steps are are spurious or not or are
good or not in the same way as uh you
know defining advantages would have
done. So I'm pretty sure you you talked
about sort of advantage weighted
regression as an offline RL method. I'm
going to do something very similar to
that uh but just sort of to kind of uh
spend one minute on the definition of of
the advantage here. So the advantage
function typically means QSA minus V of
S uh that you probably talked about. So
A of SA under a given policy is QI of SA
minus V pi of S. Uh in this particular
setting though uh the dynamics are
deterministic and the state is simply a
concatenation of the previous state with
the pre with a new set of tokens which
define the step uh that is added in
there. Hence what happens is like you
can define the advantage where as Q
value of Q value of the prefix until
step I minus Q value of the prefix until
step I minus one. Uh that sort of serves
as the same notion of advantage in this
particular MDP. So that's why the
definition you see up there is Q minus Q
and not Q minus V. But it's it's sort of
basically the same thing. So once you
define it in this way, you can actually
compute uh these advantages for every
step. So you can compute advantages by
subtracting the Q values for consecutive
steps one from each other. Uh and you'll
get some positive and some negative
numbers um in this particular setting.
Just really depends on how many times
can you succeed. And once you have these
advantages, they are a measure of how
well uh a particular step how much a
particular step contributed to your
ability to be able to succeed uh from uh
you know that particular prefix. So if
step two ended up like sort of reducing
the advantage that means uh your Q value
at [clears throat] step one was higher
than Q value after step two has been
executed which means step two is
probably not a use not that good of a
step to have in order to be able to
succeed eventually. So a negative or a
low advantage means it's a it's sort of
a bad step or kind of a spurious step
and you don't want to necessarily learn
from it. Uh a positive advantage means
it's a it's a good step and you probably
want to learn from it someday. So this
is sort of supposed to answer the
questions about like how do you identify
uh for your steps in some way. So uh the
question is are we fitting a Q function?
Um it's a very good question. Uh turns
out that in the literature there's been
two kinds of work. They explicitly fit a
Q function like quantity. uh it's what's
called uh so in the in the NLP community
this is what's called uh a process
reward model um process
reward model so in the in I'm guessing
since you covered uh DPO and and and RHF
you've talked about reward models which
sort of give you a a score for like you
know particular question and answer this
is sort of giving you the score for
every step and hence sort of like
scoring the process and hence the word
process reward model or a PRM I don't
necessarily think that PRM and Q values
are exactly or should be semantically
the same thing but that's kind of what a
lot of the NLP people call this but yeah
you can kind of train that but there's
the other class of methods which would
simply use rollouts the way I talked to
you about to estimate advantages and
we'll see what that means yeah that's a
great question the question is how does
this help learn how does this help
models learn general uh general problem
solving strategies um the rough answer
is ultimately what ends up happening
here is you are breaking down, you know,
the the success of a particular long
trace into sort of successes of
individual steps that appear inside of
it. And that can be a useful thing to
know because now uh you know presumably
your model can realize that okay once it
let's say it has broken down a problem
into four steps or four highle plans. Uh
if it can also localize which step is
kind of going wrong it can actually you
know better learn that step as opposed
to sort of you know just vaguely
thinking that okay a step three might be
the cause of the problem when it fails
whereas maybe it's actually step one. So
it helps you just learn u sort of in a
more uh so ultimately you need to have
some data for learning but then this is
sort of vastly improving your data
efficiency and so yeah
great okay so the next step is going to
be to use these advantages for training
and this is where sort of a lot of the
methods that I talked about uh also will
come in uh into picture so the first
thing is just going to be to filter by
advantages that I just described. So you
can take a bunch of traces from your
model and you know I still have the RFT
algorithm here. Um so I'm just going to
I'm going to write it down as 1 to n
sample from pi theta. You can take this
uh you can take the RFD algorithm. You
can sample uh you know you can sample
from your model and on policy trace
potentially uh you can take every step
do these rollouts that we talked about
uh use them to estimate advantages and
uh you know put this into your training
data set for doing imitation learning or
or SFT if this particular step is
correct. So what does that mean? That
basically means that you are taking a
particular trace and you are uh you are
checking for at a step level whether the
advantages are positive. Even if that
particular step comes from an incorrect
solution trace, you're going to put that
into your training data set. Uh if that
step itself gives you a high advantage
on the other hand, let's say if that
step itself uh you know comes from a
correct solution trace, maybe there's a
particular step here which gets a low
advantage or a really negative
advantage. I'm going to just throw it
away in some. So this is very much
reminiscent of advantage weighted
regression except that here rather than
doing exponentiated advantages uh which
I'm guessing was covered uh we are doing
sort of like filtering on advantages um
that's sort of the basic idea you can
also do exponentiation of advantages so
you can like you know train on
everything but multiply them multiply
the loss by E to the A. Uh that that
objective I think requires a lot of
tuning and if you can only run one
experiment you probably prefer this
objective over E to the A uh in general.
U that's a great question. So the
question is do you only train up to the
good steps on an incorrect solution? Uh
the answer is uh not really. So we
initially thought that that's kind of
the only way to train here. Uh and we
did a concrete ablation studying this as
well. The answer is well you never
really train the model to uh so so in
this particular setting you're not let's
say a particular step gives you a higher
advantage. You're not training the model
to produce this step and then this step.
All you're training is to produce this
step conditioned on the prefix so far.
So your loss looks like train the model
to produce ai given si and not the
previous actions or the previous steps
that you see up here. So um I'm just
going to probably just draw it here um
because I think it's easiest to draw it.
So think of it as this way. You had s
you had x or s0 you went to a you took a
z you went to s1 you are taking a1 you
went to s2. These are steps and this is
the the states you're not let's say this
state get got an advantage which is
really positive. So a of s1 a1 is really
positive and a of s0 a z is really
negative. What you are going to do now
is you're going to not necessarily so
what I'm not saying is train on train
your policy to produce a z given s0.
You're not going to do that. You're
going to just train the policy to
produce a1 given s0 a z. So that's all
you're trying or you know I wrote S0
comma A0 this basically just is equal to
S1 because you're concatenating steps
but that's kind of the thing you're
going to incentivize. So you're only
training on the steps.
So the question is uh is there a
separate prompter that keeps prompting
the model when it acts here? Uh the
answer is not really right. So um in
general when you do RL we never really
train the policy to sort of uh we we
train a policy you know with to to
produce individual actions like in
offline RL or invitation learning. We
train it to produce A1 given S1, A2
given S2 and so on. But when it acts in
the world, it just acts and produce a
giant string of token or giant sequence
of actions in one go. Right? So you can
train the policy on different segments
of steps it's uh it's seeing. But at
when it's deployed, it's going to just
produce one action. Then you know the
the the state S1 is going to be simply
the the whole uh you know tokens in the
question, tokens in the action, tokens
in the step so far, and that's S1. And
you're going to now the same policy can
now continue on and produce the next
step. So it's not going to be prompted
in any way. It's just like going to be
producing the whole solution in one flow
except that now you're just training it
in a way that uh you know you're
breaking them down into steps. So really
there's no notion of like a separate
actor. So the question is do you only
train on a step because of the markoff
property um because you don't care how
you got there. Uh in a way the answer is
uh or actually no because in some ways
your state S1 consists of all of your
history, right? So s1 consists of uh so
s0 is a problem
a z is let's say step one and s1 in this
case is basically problem concatenated
with state uh with step one right
so in some ways you have preserved all
of your history in in this case and it's
a non-marovian policy that you're
learning except that here uh the reason
why we do this at the step level is
because now we can better do better
understand which part of the solution
actually u you caused me to derail if if
if it did. So there's no notion of like
independence. It's not like given S so
okay in in this particular setting given
S1 sure action A1 is all matters but S1
and S0 A0 are the same. It's so it's
it's depending upon the way you look at
it it can be called a non-mark policy as
well because it's conditioned on the
whole history but in this particular
setting if you define S1 as concatenated
states it's a markov policy. Um so the
question is if your Q value is really um
so your Q values are really negative but
your advantages are positive would do
you put it in the training data set or
not. Uh yeah that's a great question. Uh
I think we we we tried this uh with like
uh so we we did take traces which were
incorrect and we took we we put the the
steps which were actually good from them
uh into our data set. Um and that was
fine except that like let's say if there
are traces where everything is just a Z
like there there's no way like there's
no prefix of that from which you can
succeed at all. The advantages are also
small and the QRS are also small. Turns
out that if you filter them out you
might do a little bit better. Uh but
again I don't have a very very concrete
like result I can show you here. So I'm
not going to like tell you that this is
the way to go. But like it seems like to
a large extent the sensitivity does not
exist in some way because you're you
know the prefix is the culprit then and
you're training only A1 conditioned on
the on the prefix and not train the
model to produce the prefix at all. Okay
great. Uh so so that's the first option.
So this is a lot like filtered imitation
learning or advantage beta regression.
The next thing okay before that I can
show you some results here. So uh this
actually ended up uh addressing that
error going up problem uh at least to
the extent that we were able to train
models. So uh you know here uh again I'm
plotting number of correct answers per
question and you find that the advantage
filtering did help you u compared to
sort of uh the the the RFD approach
which was going up before um so it does
actually and and we did measure the
number of spurious steps according to
some heristic definition of you know how
we can evaluate this like how can we can
probe this and seemed like just from a
qualitative perspective also the number
of spurious steps actually kind of
reduced in some uh in some way.
Okay, so the next thing is how can you
use this for offline reinforcement
learning and and this is where sort of
uh you know DPO based methods come in.
So there was a question about this
earlier uh in the class. So you can also
use them for for you can also use the
same principle for doing DPO actually.
So the idea in DPO uh is uh sort of
slightly different from computing this
advantage exactly but uses the same
protocol that I described to you earlier
where what you're going to do now is
you're going to you know take a solution
from your base model u that you're that
you're training uh maybe this is
incorrect uh and so far what we did was
we found out steps that were useful and
retained them in some way or the other
and discarded everything else. But what
we can do now is we can do these
rollouts uh and rather than sort of
throwing away uh you know or or throwing
away these rollouts or just using these
rollouts to estimate the advantage. What
I can do is I can instead take a roll
out which ended up succeeding uh you
know with a shared prefix take the
solution trace from my model which did
not end up succeeding and construct a
preference pair out of them. So I now
have a preference pair which looks like
you know some prefix followed by some
correction which is good and some prefix
followed by sort of like some steps
which are actually wrong and I can throw
this into a DPO training data set in
some I can also do the same thing with
like sort of a correct rollout. So if
let's say I have a correct roll out from
my base model uh I can still do these
rollouts uh you know and maybe one of
them will not end up succeeding uh
potentially uh from my rollout policy
and I can basically put uh this thing as
a preference pair into my uh into my
training mix.
So the nice thing that is happening or
there are two differences that are
happening here right in some way I'm
still realizing in this process that
prefixes are shared and really the
difference between you know correct and
incorrect rollout comes from that little
segment that you see uh you know beyond
the prefix uh in the in in these
settings that's the first thing and the
second thing is you know rather than the
previous approach of filtering by
advantages I'm actually retaining the
whole steps that appear in this roll out
distribution. So I'm not simply using
these rollouts like the the the orange
colored uh you know dash lines to
compute advantages but I'm retaining
them and I'm training on top of the
tokens that appear in that roll out as
well. So uh the DPO loss I guess I don't
have that on my slides but you know I
guess probably uh you know I don't need
to necessarily write that down but it's
basically just a matter of like you know
the same old DPO loss on top of these
two segments of of solutions that we uh
talked about. Yeah, great question. So
the question is do you want higher
quality text or do you want sort of more
diversity? Um I think the the true uh so
I uh okay so u I should mention that
like this is something that we have
tried to formalize. So there's like an
exact equation that you can you can
write down and you can be like okay I
want a policy to do these rollouts which
maximizes this expression um sort of
thing in in one of the papers. Um I
think that kind of balances in some way
diversity and high quality. So imagine
for a second that your model is really
bad. So let's say your model mostly
produces incorrect traces. Then you want
a rollout policy that can actually
somewhat succeed because otherwise
there's no notion of a success that you
can learn from ever, right? You've only
seen failures. How can you actually even
learn to solve that problem if you only
see failures? Uh on the other hand,
let's say if your model is kind of
decent, like 50% accurate, but it's like
you know not as good overall, like it's
not the best at solving problems. In
that case, maybe all you want is just
diverse ways of solving the problem such
that you can see what ways you're more
prone to failing. So you care about
about sort of coverage in some ways. So
really the answer here is like every
single problem in RL there is some
balance between exploration and
exploitation you kind of want to do
which is highquality text or highquality
solutions which solve the question
correctly and you know being more being
more uh diverse in some way. Um I think
the exact expression for this is
actually something you can also write
down. Um and uh I'm not going to cover
today but yeah it's a it's trade-off
between them. Yeah. So they basically
used to train DPU. So so you know like
so far I guess okay actually let me just
write that algorithm down for
everybody's understanding. Um so what
you do is you're basically so that is
the RFT algorithm and now what we are
going to do is we going to simply do the
same process. So for iteration
in 1 to t I'm going to you know sample
y 1 to n from my current policy
uh given any question I am going to now
do these rollouts. So I'm going to you
know do rollouts
and uh you know construct the preference
data set dref uh in this case it's
basically those preferences and and now
what I'm going to do is I'm going to do
run or minimize DPO loss.
Um that's kind of the main algorithm
that you're going to do and the the deep
ref consists of you know sol prefixes
generated from your current base model
and the traces coming from sort of you
know one part of it is from the same
model that you are training pi theta the
other segment the other part of the
preference pair comes from the rollout
policy that does the orange line. So the
question is given a sample trajectory
how do we segment into steps. So in this
work we just used sentences. So we just
said well sentences we going to break
them down into steps from after every
sentence. uh in general I think uh it
depends it's a thing that you can bake
into your model. So if if you if you
have played with for example open AI
models you'll see that they often
produce responses that look like you
know step one in sort of markdown like a
very big step one and then they'll say a
bunch of stuff and then step two and
they'll say a bunch of stuff. So you can
use that sort of notation. oftenimes uh
it's it's so happening that as these
models kind of get better at basic
instruction following you can just
prompt them to produce responses for
complex questions in a particular
stylistic fashion and use some huristics
about that style to partition things
into steps. So for instance, you can
just tell a model well I want an answer
that uh for for this particular question
that uh you know that never uses the
word step that always uses that always
you know produces a logical block of
calculation puts a puts a horizontal
line and then pushes the next logical
block and so on and it'll most likely do
it for you. Uh which is something you
can also do during the course of
training. So you can just prompt them to
kind of produce solutions in a
particular way and then define steps
accordingly. There's no universal
definition.
So the question is is there a convention
to produce special tokens for generating
steps? Um I think that I've not seen a
very very clear convention that's
universally used all the time. One
convention that we have been using that
I've seen many other papers use but
there are still outliers for this is
they would produce like step hash one
colon and then say something and that
could be bunch of lines as well. Um you
know in this work we used lines in in a
follow-up thing we we had used this like
step notion. So it really depends on
like up to you really I think. Yeah.
Okay. Uh, cool. Any questions on the DPO
part uh in this case? So, this is the
the DPO version of the algorithm.
Uh, great. Okay. So, you can do this uh
and uh and put this into your into your
data. So, if you go back to our our plot
from before, if you measure how how well
does such kind of an offline RL method
do, uh what ends up happening is okay, I
guess these were supposed to be gifs,
but anyways. Uh so I'm now plotting the
test error as a function of number of
questions that existed in my data set.
So you know so far we were looking at
number of correct answers per question
for a lot of the plots in the in the
middle. But now I'm back to the plot
where we are plotting the x-axis as a
function of number of questions uh in
the original data set. And you find that
compared to uh and now there are two
models here. One of them is like a llama
2 model. So this is probably tells you
how old this work is at this point. uh
it's it's a year old but llama 2 is like
feels like long time ago um and then
deepseek v2 models as well as uh yeah
deepse v2 models and what we finding in
general is that compared to the base sft
method where you were just training on
human written solutions you can get up
to an 8x boost in the amount of data
that you need for training. So uh the
dashed line here is this per step sort
of DPO algorithm that I talked about and
you see that uh it can get you the same
test error with like 8x fewer samples
than uh than like training with SFT on
on like human written data. Uh RF was 2x
for for recollection. We I removed that
line here because it would have been too
cluttered. Uh but in general like this
8x also holds true for lama 2 roughly uh
overall in this setting. Yeah. So the
question is what is pass at five? That's
a great uh that's a great question. uh
so you can think of passet five I guess
for understanding this slide it doesn't
matter first of all but in general you
can think of passet five basically as
saying if I gave the model five chances
can it succeed even once out of those
five chances so it's sort of a a way
people evaluate models because it's kind
of telling you that okay maybe the model
could not succeed in one try but if I
give it like five n tries maybe it can
succeed and that's what pass at n means
the setting it doesn't I mean I don't
think for this particular result it
matters so much the main thing to look
at is this 8x kind of boost in data
efficiency that you up here.
Okay. So the high level takeaway here is
that if you do offline RL with sort of
this per step notion of like credit
assignment that we talked about uh you
can actually do sort of uh you can
actually get a lot more data efficiency
boost compared to imitation learning. So
for the same amount of data for the same
base model or sorry for the same base
model and for 8x fewer questions you can
do similar you can get the same
performance with with RL in this
setting. Yeah. So generally I've seen
people use 6 as a temperature for a lot
of the So the question is what's the
temperature recommended temperature to
use. I've generally found it to be 6 is
what most people use. I don't think that
there's like a there's like a something
that's like set in stone. You can always
change it someplace
solid the solid. So the question is
what's a solid line? That's just SFD on
like human written solutions in this
setting. There's no per step advantage
on that line. Yeah. Uh and the first
step advantage one was actually the one
I showed you before. I removed it here
because sort of like this is the kind of
maybe the the ultimate kind of result in
some ways from human data to kind of
self-generated data of sorts but yeah
it's like 2x the with the first step
yeah
okay so the final thing uh that you know
final main method and then I'm going to
just talk about what people are
currently doing very briefly and I'll
end the lecture at that point but the
final thing we can also do here is
online reinforcement learning there's
two ways of doing this uh sort of the
most basic recipe for doing this is
actually to not use any of this
advantage age but sort of generalize
this kind of basic RFT algorithm without
advantages to online error. So how do
you do that? You can basically just you
know take uh your your model you know
similar to like how we sampled a bunch
of traces from my current model or
current policy and filter the right ones
rather than filtering you can just train
it with like on policy RL. So you can
just generate uh rollouts from your
current policy uh you know uh which
might be correct or wrong. Uh you know
one of the you can reward them using
like the reward function by just
checking the answer against the the
answer that the model produces. You can
penalize it if it does not produce an
answer. You can penalize it if it
violates format. There's bunch of like
reward uh shaping things you can do and
then you just like train your policy to
maximize this reward using policy
gradients. So RF was we were we were
explicitly filtering and and training
with SFT but rather than doing this
filtering or training with SFT you can
simply run on policy reinforcement
learning because all in this formulation
is just state action there's an MDP
there's a reward and just do R on top of
it. So you know you can simply write the
policy gradient gradient equation. So
that basically just looks like grad log
pi times the reward uh that you see up
here. Uh and you can just run that on
your problem. Um uh there's also a lot
of work which now tries to kind of go
beyond the basic reinforce style policy
gradient and goes to sort of methods
like what's called gRPO. It's nothing
but just an extension of like the basic
PPO algorithm uh in the setting. So the
PP algorithm I guess I'm going to say a
few things like PP algorithm uses a
learned value function. The GRPU
algorithm replaces that learned value
function or learned q value function
with simply this rollout based
estimation of advantages. So the same
old basic RL recipe applied on an MDP
that looks like the thing that you see
up there. So a trajectory that looks
like the thing that you see up there
with a 01 reward. Okay. And what you can
also do uh and this is something that
finally you can do is you can also do
per step advantages in online RL. Um
that's kind of the final method that you
can apply. So in this setting you can
take a solution from your base model.
You know you or take a solution from
your current policy that you're training
or over the course of training. You can
do these rollouts if you want to. You
can use these rollouts to compute
advantages uh and rather than doing
these rollouts, you can also potentially
do something slightly different u and
which is basically to train a reward
model like thing to fit to these
advantage predictions or fit to fit to
these Q value predictions and then
compute advantages. So this is very
similar to sort of the RLHF work that
you probably saw uh except that now this
is a reward model that is rewarding
every step uh of sorts or that or reward
model that's producing the Q value for
every step or the advantage for every
step as opposed to producing a reward
for the whole sequence that you are
seeing. And once you have these uh
advantage predictions that you can fit
to a network, you can query this uh
particular uh so for any rollout that
your policy produces, you can query the
advantage predictor that you have
trained to reward every single step uh
in this particular policy generation.
And once you do that uh what you can do
now is you can simply you know take your
network produce these advantage labels
and optimize for reward that you're
getting at the end plus these advantages
that you see up here uh in this set.
Yeah, that's a great So the question is
uh how generalizable is reasoning? When
you train on math, does it improve on
GSM8K? So turns out if you train on
math, it does not improve on GSM 8K and
many people have shown it. But if you
train on uh a bunch of mixture of
prompts which are of varied levels of
difficulty, you can actually get there.
So this is precisely the recipe which
has been used in in and or not this one
but the the basic online order recipe
which I talked to you about earlier uh
used to train all of these uh or many of
these thinking models who have uh which
have like open you know open recipe
descriptions. So this online auto recipe
is kind of used to train the deepc
carbon model for instance and that kind
of does generalize to a fairly good
amount of extent. It doesn't also
generalize to a large to every single
problem out there but to a fairly good
extent it does. So you can compute these
you know advantage predictions you can
fit them to a network use them to
produce these rewards for every single
step and that's sort of the more
advanced way of doing online RL uh in
with this particular thing. So we had a
work that we call process advantage
verifiers here uh process because uh you
know it's rewarding every step advantage
because it's fitting an advantage
function and a verifier because uh in
somehow in the domain of reasoning
reward models are referred to often as
verifiers. So if you see that word come
up just it's it's just synonymous to a
reward model of sorts or in this
particular case even you can think of it
as a Q function or a value function of
sorts. So, but that's kind of the name
of the method. And you know, we find
that in general um so I'm going to skip
some of these details, but in general,
if you do uh dense reward RL like
process reward or advantage based reward
uh RL, you find that you can kind of get
to a much better accuracy uh compared to
sort of what's called OM RL or just 01
reward RL like the sparse 01 reward
provided at the end. Right? So this is
sort of the basic recipe that a lot of
the current work is using. This is sort
of the advantage based verifiers recipe
and you can kind of see that you can get
a bigger boost in sample efficiency as
well as uh in terms of uh just absolute
performance that you see up here. Also
these numbers kind of look small but uh
like with 2B and 9B models that we were
basing this off of apparently like this
is sort of the best result that you can
get uh on certain data sets that we
tried this on. So it's about 5 to 6x
sample efficiency boost and about six to
7% absolute performance improvement uh
in this particular setting with the
dense advantages in some way.
Okay. Uh okay I'm going to skip some of
these things but at a high level uh you
know we we are also seeing now these
like newer uh thinking models that have
come up where basically these models can
just think for longer and produce a
better answer. This is sort of the DeepC
R1 family of models, the open O1 family
of models or O series O series of models
from OpenAI. In my opinion, uh like
really these are trained using very
similar recipes that I just talked to
you about for this whole lecture except
that there are some small changes that
happen uh in this in this process from
like you know pre uh pre these models
era versus these models. So the RL
training objective has remained the
same. So you know there's some minor
details like uh there's this new method
called GRPO which I just just
describing. It's basically PO with some
tweaks. Uh there's also some other
methods like advantage induced policy
alignment. You don't you don't need to
know what those methods are. Just think
of them roughly as policy gradient
methods done with slight tweaks overall.
But what has changed is that the action
space in a way has changed for these
models in my opinion. Now this is a very
kind of crude statement to make and to
be fair to be to be really rigorous
about it. I think the statement sounds
wrong because these models do actually
produce token by token one at a time.
But these models, the base models on
which we are doing RL have become better
at being able to kind of uh implement
interesting kind of meta procedures like
you know these met these models can
actually produce a solution maybe go out
there and then try to like verify the
solution they have produced maybe then
backtrack to a particular point and do
something else from there. And you can
think of this as just yet another
version of like defining the step like
these models can produce more
interesting steps than just going out
there and calculating yet another
quantity like the models previously
could have done. So it's just a better
notion of a step or a better action uh
that these models can sample when you
run all of these algorithms on top of
them. And once you do that and you give
these models a longer budget to act. So
if you tell these models that okay
there's no limit on how many tokens you
can you can think uh you you can sample
during the course of RL you can maybe
sample solutions which are really really
long but just get me the right answer if
I give these models that playground to
kind of sample more and more tokens
turns out that RL training algorithms
with you know with these two bullet
points actually give you much better
performance and that's kind of what we
see with these current thinking models
right now turns out that if these models
are uh you know if you if you do a
counterfactual experiment where you take
models which are not capable at doing
you know implementing like basic sort of
answer checking or verification or
generating a better answer. Turns out
that you cannot do good RL with them
right now. So really nothing has changed
in terms of like the higher level
techniques that I talked about except
that the base models have become more
have become more interesting in a way
that they can sample interesting kinds
of steps to train on and that has led to
some of the most amazing results that we
are seeing right now.